[Music]
let's denote the set of parameters by
Theta so I'm going to come up with some
kind of a performance measure for a specific
choice of theta so I'll call it EA of theta
right so for what is a specific choice of theta
correspond to suppose my Theta is like composed
of theta 1 theta2 Theta K so I give you values
for Theta 1 Theta 2 theta 3 up to Theta K so
what does this correspond to one policy okay when
I say I'm looking at a specific value for Theta
it corresponds to one policy so when I say EA
of theta that means I'm evaluating that policy
somehow okay so what is the most natural
evaluation measure you can think of for a
policy the expected payoff
right the expected expected payoff is
the evaluation for the policy so yeah
I'm going to do I'm going to do that there okay
so what is the expected payoff you
know what the expected pay off is
this is the expected payoff I get for
taking action a this is a probability
that I'll take action a when I'm selecting
actions according to Theta right right so
this is a standard notation I I don't
know if people are familiar with this
this means Pi is a function that's parameterized
by Theta right and whatever specific value I give
for Theta will Define what that Pi is okay and
then this means it's going to take some other
argument okay so this is the input to the function
okay which is defined by these parameters Theta
okay so this is how I when you put a semicolon
here that means it is parameterized form okay
okay your arms are tied from taking all
the notes that's all okay fine uh yeah so
so essentially Pi a semicolon Theta means
that is the policy defined by the current
settings of parameters Theta times the Q star
a right because qar is a true expectation for
taking arm a right and then some over all a I'll
basically get the expected but if I'm having a
deterministic policy that means essentially
only one arm I'll take all the other arms of
probability is zero then the payoff will be Q
star of that arm right okay great okay so now
once I have this kind of a performance measure
so what do I do is essentially I take Theta
okay I take Theta I find the gradient of
the performance okay so where the gradient
is taken with respect to Theta right so I
look at how the performance changes with
changing Theta and I'll try to move Theta
in the direction of the increase in the
performance okay so this is called gradient
Ascent the people might have heard about
gradient descent earlier so this is gradient
Ascent so I'm going up the gradient right if
the performance improves if I change Theta in
some direction then I'll change my Theta in that
direction okay does that make sense people
see this or do you need more pictorial
analogies right so let's say
that I have one parameter Theta okay
let say I have one parameter Theta right
and that's e of theta let's say
this my uh this is a good way to do
it right let's say that I have my performance
whatever is an acceptable range of theta so my
performance goes like this right so I initially
start off with some guess for Theta and that
will be my initial guess for Theta right then
what I do I measure this and then I compute
the gradient right so the gradient is there so if
I look at which direction I should move my Theta
so essentially I should move in this direction
so I move a little bit and set that as Theta
one okay then I measure the gradient again
okay still I have to move in this direction
more so I keep doing that and I
think I I'll declare that I have
reached the highest performance
there so this is essentially how
I do it okay so there are a couple
of questions which you might ask me
here why do I have to do this in this kind
of an incremental fashion why can't I just
take the derivative of that and find
the highest point and settle down there
sorry I don't have the function at all forget
about close form I don't have that function
at all what is that function that is qar a *
pi right I know Pi but I don't know qar if I
know qar my problem is solved right I don't
need to do any of these things that function
itself I don't know right so how am I evaluating
this function and trying to find the gradient
by sampling so I'm pulling a lot of arms right
according to my current policy P right and then
I'm trying to evaluate the policy pi and trying
to find a gradient at that point right so because
everything is done through sampling so whatever
gradient I compute at this point will not be the
correct gradient right I this is too simple
I mean it has to either be that direction or
this direction this is too simple right but
think of a multi-dimensional Cas when there
are many many parameters the right direction
you have compute can get messed up right so
instead of going in all the parameters inste of
identifying the right direction some parameters
you might get the right direction some parameters
you will get the wrong direction and so on so
forth right therefore every time you make only
small steps because if you try if you say oh I
have computed the direction of the gradient I'll
just keep moving in the direction until my or or
I'll take a huge step in the direction until
my performance drops or something that won't
work because the direction itself might be wrong
right so in this case I mean we' always moved in
the right direction every every step but it
is possible that because you're estimating
the gradient you might actually make the wrong
computations and move in the wrong direction
sometimes okay so what uh really you can hope
for from these kinds of methods which are
called stochastic gradient approaches
okay they're called stochastic gradient
approaches because you don't know the
true gradient and every time you make
an estimate of what the true gradient
will be and then you're using that
for making mov so I mean the most popular
form of this will be called SGD which is
stochastic gradient descent okay it's a very
popular optimization technique nowadays but
in this case you're using stochastic gradient
Ascent okay but still it's the same stochastic
gradient idea and so you have to be careful
about how you use it and the best that you
can hope to get is that in an expected sense
over many many updates right I did I did know I
two updates so if you make this updates
these kinds of updates many many times in
an expected sense you will move in the right
direction of the gradient right so that is the
kind of guarantee that typically you expect
for these kinds of methods okay is it clear
now it's clearer now right people are not 100%
clear about what I'm talking just stop and ask
right I can elaborate at the risk of slowing
down yeah how exactly we estimate the gradi
good point yeah so we'll come to that so we can
talk about that so if we don't know the function
itself right how are you going to estimate
the gradient right so we'll come to that in a
minute
uh so we know we have a functional form
for this now I'm going to write down the
the gradient for this expression right this is the
expression we have I'm going to write
down the gradient for this expression
so this is assuming that qar a because it's a
parameter of the problem right it has nothing
to do with the policy right as far as your policy
parameterization is concern Q star is a constant
right because it's a it's something to do with the
problem so I can I don't have to do this I just
have to differentiate this with respect to Theta
right so now I'm going to do some um hand waving
so what did I do here I multiplied and
divided by pi okay so for this to work
what do I need Pi is non zero for all a
so this is one condition that you need
for all of this any kind of Pi that you
assume okay has to be non zero for all a
just AUM some some nonzero probity now if
you think about this particular expression
right I'll put a bracket around that
right so what does this remind you
of does it look like an expectation
computation I'm looking at the expected
value of some function right where I'm
taking samples according to probability pi
right this looks like an expected value right
I'm summing over all possible outcomes of a
all possible values here right right that
is a probability so I'm essentially taking
the expectation taken according
to Pi of
is it
fine right so everybody on board
with it right so that I can write
their expectation oh okay sorry about the font
so the expectation is taken with respect to Pi
okay is it clear so now we know how to make an
estimate of the expectations right how do we
do that we draw sample and then take an average
right so we can do that so essentially
what I'm going to do is pull an
arm that's a sample right when you say draw a
sample according to Pi that essentially means
I have to pull an arm right and what happens when
I pull an arm I get a reward right but the reward
does not figure in here the expectation of the
reward directly figures in here right so I can
actually write this as a double expectation
you know mean the the expectation is taken
over not only Pi but also over the process
that generates the reward Q Star right it's
also the process that generates the reward
so my sample here is going to consist of
RT right is is it clear I mean this is
a very subtle thing people are with me
here on this is it clear see qar itself is
already an expectation right so instead of
because I don't know this expectation I have
estimate this expectation as well and that can
be done by just taking the RTS so what I'll do
now is at every time T I'll sample an arm I'll
pull the arm figure out what the reward is right
but is that sufficient no I have to do this right
so I just can't use the RT directly I have to
use this also right so I'll take the gradient of
Pi so evaluated at a divide
by the so this is my one
sample right is is clear because
the expectation I'm taking is of
this quantity so the sample that I draw is
actually this right and I have to do this
over I don't know some number
in p 0 you're
right just fine so oh no no
no no no I'm not using T I'm
sorry so I promised you that I'll use n for
discrete time and T for continuous time so
we're talking about discrete times here it
has to be N I don't know if I use T here
sorry about that but uh all of you erase in your
notebook the T and write down n for this part of
think it's okay sorry about that right so
is this clear is there anything missing
right so I need to have 1 byn there so this gives
me the gradient right so this is fine are we still
okay if not because this is
actually a estimation okay
so I can't put equal to there it's only an
approximation okay great so can we compute
this we can right because we know Pi we
are the ones who determine what pi should
be right because at the beginning I choose a
parameterized representation right I can choose
whatever suppose it's soft Max well I know how
to take the derivative of softmax or if it's a
continuous actions I can just use a say a goian
right I know how to take the derivative of a
goian with respect to its parameters right or
if it's a multinomial what do I do we know how
to take the derivative of a multinomial as
well right so the derivative is very simple
so so I know what form of the function I
choose it so I can go ahead and take the
derivative there are a couple of reasons for it
uh so estimating Q star need not always be the
right thing to do okay uh I not introduced all
the complications I'm hesitating whether I should
go there or not uh but the thing is um so the qar
function sometimes turns out to be incredibly
complex okay as a function of the state space
okay not necessarily here right as a function
of the state space Q turns out to be incredibly
complex whereas a direct representation of the
policy turns out to be a lot more simple right
for example uh there are many inventory control
problems where the policy essentially turns out
to be if the inventory is below a certain level
you buy inventory is above a certain level you
don't buy okay but then the value function itself
becomes a very complicated function of how many of
the items are left of different types and so on so
forth the function itself becomes a lot harder to
learn so there are instances like this where this
is easier to learn right and there are a couple of
other uh cases um especially when you're talking
about very large problems for example uh we'll
see that policy gradient approaches generalize
very easily to problems with continuous actions
so where there are individual action so but
if I'm talking about value function methods
right where I typically store a value for each
Action Now him going to have continuous actions
it's not clear how to handle it there are ways of
handling it but it turns out that uh they are not
that well behaved as policy gradient approaches
are and the action space is continuous right so
there are many reasons why you want to consider
the continuous actions I mean policy gr methods
primarily I would say the one of the primary
motivations is to handle uh continuous actions
okay so this is some kind of a batch batch
updates uh because the expectation
is taken with respect to the
pi are
the
um yeah you could do more simplifications of that
if you want to right but uh what is your question
again no but I need to take this expectation
with respect to the samp the the probability
distribution PI right so um and I I I
can't separate this I can't write this
out as a some I really can't simplify this
further because my qar is here right so this
is the expectation of this whole quantity so
I really can't split this apart and say that
okay I'll just simplify this expectation and
take only the expected value of qar a can I
I can't take e of a b is not a
into e of B is it if a is only
a constant right not otherwise I'm not
sure that you can simplify this further
uh right so what we are doing here is some
kind of a batch mode so if you think of how
we are doing this sampling so I am taking some
Theta fixing it pulling arms multiple times
right I'm fixing Theta pulling arms
capital N times and then taking this
average right and then or Computing the
gradient and then using that to change
the parameters this is one way of doing it
another way of doing it to say that okay
I'll have a Theta I'll pull an arm I'll
compute the gradient and I'll change the
parameters right so you can
have a some kind of an increment
version right so where I'm saying at
every step I'll change my parameters
by some fraction delta T
I'll do this at every step
right sorry
so this is what I'm doing so what I'm essentially
will end up doing is uh Theta will be theta plus
Delta Theta right Theta n + 1 will be Theta n plus
Delta Theta n right so this basically what I'm
saying right I'll do this at every time for
every time I pull an off I'll change this
right I mean that is essentially the gradient of
the lawn it turns out this simplifies your life a
lot this observation simplifies your life a lot
when you're trying to actually solve the solve
problems later right now you can immed immediately
think of soft Max becoming very easy to
differentiate now taken lawn and
there's Al lots of e there right
so all the E power will thing will
vanish so it will become lot easier
to differentiate for you right so what I'm
going to do now is to include another term
here rather arbitrarily
called
BN which we refer to as the reinforcement
Baseline right and adding the BN should
not affect the whole process therefore
the BN should not really be a function
OFA a uh yeah Theta basically so should not
be a function of the action I take right if
it's a function of the action I take then it
becomes dependent on uh Theta so as long as
it's not a function of the action I take I can
keep adding a I can add this thing it's called
the reinforcement Baseline right so one way of
thinking about it is I'm when I get a reward
right I don't know if the reward is a good reward
or a bad reward so giving a Baseline and saying
that if you're above this Baseline it's a good
reward if you're below this Baseline it's is a
bad reward okay kind of allows you to Cal Cate the
rewards right one uh uh typical way in which this
reinforcement Baseline is used is to just take
the average of all the rewards I have obtained
so far right this is all the rewards regardless
of which arm I played I keep accumulating the
rewards right now when I play a particular arm
if it is above this average then it is a good
arm if it's below this average then it's a bad
arm right valid after aaging after after yeah
only it's fine eventually it'll eventually it'll
be all fine right so initially you might be making
some mistakes because initial few the the B
will be wrong right uh so you might actually
think a good arm is bad and a bad arm is good I
mean depending but eventually it will all work
out doesn't matter right so if think about if
the reward is good right then I will go in the
direction of the gradient right if the reward is
bad and it'll go in the opposite direction of the
gradient right so in some sense that's a little
waving here that but then it's fine it turns out
that adding the reinforcement Baseline uh makes
the convergence behavior of this algorithm a
little more stable okay but it is not necessary
you can if you're going to implement this you
can do it without the reinforcement
Baseline also right so this is called
the and this term is sometimes called
the called the characteristic eligibility
so what is the characteristic
eligibility it essentially tells
you if you do that then you get into actor critic
I'll talk about that later I'll talk about that
later yeah sure yeah you could do that right and
that's essentially the one of the motivations for
getting into ttic algorithms so that is requires
you to maintain a qar estimates as well as the pi
estimates as well as a pi representation so the
pi would be the critic and the qar would be the
actor other way don't the pi would be the actor
the qar would be the critic so that's another
class of algorithms right which address some of
the drawbacks of policy gradient approaches right
so I'll talk about it uh but somewhere halfway
down the course not now so after this I'm going
to go back and start talking about for the full
RL problem and at some point I'll come back and
do actor critic yeah so his question was why do
I use RN right why can't I plug-in Q there right
you could and uh yeah and typically when you
do that it performs better the algorithm it's
actually it reduces variance significantly
at the cost of adding uh significant buys
right and uh yeah there are other
other issues you know you well you
know what are the other issues going
to act critic but I'll talk about it
later right anyway going back uh so
why is that called the characteristic
eligibility so if you think about it so it
essentially chooses which of the thetas are
most responsible for a change at that point right
so that is the term that determines that is the
term that is the Theta dependent term in your
updates right and it tells you which Theta is
more responsible for change that is happening here
there are three or four different parameters that
I have right so whichever has the highest gradient
whichever direction you have the highest gradient
that is a direction where the largest change is
going to happen right so essentially it is telling
you which Theta is more eligible to receive the
update that's why it's called the characteristic
eligibility right did that make sense to people I
think I've lost more people
today than in the previous
classes no great uh so this whole
thing right this this way of doing
this incremental version of doing
this update is actually called the
called the reinforce algorithm was first proposed
by this guy called Williams in um 88 uh Williams
repos uh reinforce uh in I think in 1988 and in
fact he proposed this in the context of neural
networks right so he when he came up with this
algorithm neural networks were uh still ruling
right so he proposed this in the context of
neural network he said that your thetas are
weights of a neural network right and then he
came up with this update and then the the the
biggest contribution he did was uh he said that
hey this looks like a really crazy update right
I mean how is this going to work and initially
people are very skeptical he actually showed
that in an expected sense that even though
I'm doing this update after just pulling one
arm okay in an expected sense the gradient will
be in the right direction right if if I repeat
this experiment multiple times and I watch how
the weights evolve right they'll actually move
in the same direction as it would have happened
if I had computed the correct gradient and then
taken steps in that direction so essentially he
established that uh for this reinforce update
and it since then it has kind of been uh the one
sole hope of convergence for all kinds of complex
function approximations and RL okay so it works
um works really well but it's extra extremely
slow reinforce is extremely slow because the
variance is very high okay so when I want to move
on from this I'll talk about the other problems of
reinforce here is a horrible part about the paper
uh so reinforce is actually an acronym there's an
expansion each letter stands actually for a word
so he came up with a name for the algorithm
which actually shortened to reinforce okay
and then that started the trend for convoluted
names inal Community okay so anyone knows what
the expansion of reinforce do you know what
the expansion of reinforce is forgot okay
yeah I I I I can't for the life of me I refuse
to memorize what reinforce stands for okay great
so let us do some uh special cases of uh uh
reinforce right uh I want to consider a binary
Bandit okay or let's say I take a bandit with two
actions okay but they can
have arbitrary rewards okay
so here is the parameterization I choose
this is essentially the the berol thing
right so I have two actions so some
probability Theta I'll select action
one 1 minus Theta I'll select action zero okay
so what do I need to do now to get that update
rule have to find Long Pi
by Theta so what this will be
it will be one if a is 1 it'll
beus one
if correct no yeah looking La PI right it's
not Pi by Theta long Pi by do theta yeah so
it will be 1 by Theta of here is 1 and
it will be - 1 by 1 - th if a is zero
right can write it like that substitute a is 1 so
1us Theta 1- Theta will get cancel out you'll get
1 by Theta you subtitute a is z Theta and Theta
will get cancel out you'll get - 1 by 1us Theta
okay very compact way of writing it and
now I'm going to say that I'll
choose my Alpha to be some row
* Theta into 1us
Theta so it turns out that as long as your
Alpha is not dependent on the actual reward
that you get okay it can be dependent on
the Theta this is what Williams showed as
long as it's not dependent on the actual
reward you all fine okay you will converge
so that's essentially the result so I can
make it dependent on my Theta it should not
be dependent on the uh the actual action you
sampled okay and the actual reward that you
received so as long as that is there it's
fine all right and I'm going to choose my
B to be zero why why I making
this specific choices so now
let me plug everything back in
so what does my Delta Theta look
like so alpha n which is row into
Theta and 1us Theta into RN minus
B which is zero so it's RN into do on this which
will be a minus Theta by Theta into 1us
Theta right so what do I end up getting
row okay so what is what is the interpretation for
this let us say I take action one okay and
I get a reward of one so what do I get row
into 1us Theta that is how much I change
my value by so which is essentially this
right row into 1us Theta right suppose I took
action uh what what about I took action one
right and my reward was one right what will I
do for uh zero oh there's no there's only one
parameter right so automatically my other
parameter will get adjusted because it's
1us Theta suppose I took action one
and got a rward of zero what happens
no change suppose I took an action
of zero and got a reward of one what
happens minus Theta into RN right so
that's essentially what I have here
right so this is minus Theta into RN right
so Theta is my P T8 if you remember right
and then this is so that's essentially
what I have so this is this this is what
L
right so essentially L is a it's a gradient
following algorithm actually it's a reinforced
algorithm right so you can try to look at
different choices for the uh the uh uh alphas
and the different choices for PI right and try
to come up with these kinds of update rules right
we'll do the soft Max action selection as I
described in the previous class right so do
that right where I replace all my Q's with some
arbitrary Theta suppose I have K actions or k
arms then I'll have Theta 1 2 Theta K these are
my parameters and the probability of selecting
arm I will be E power Theta I by Beta divided
by summation over J e^ Theta J by vaa right so
this is my soft Max expression so derive my
reinforce update rules assuming that's the
expression right that's one
I'm going to give you another
homework the same
thing so I said one of the nice
things about uh doing reinforce
is said it allows us to handle
continuous actions right it
allows us to handle continuous action
actions need not be discrete so far
we have been looking at the cases where
actions are discrete so I'm going to use
that is my probability
distribution that is my policy
okay give me the reinforce update
rules so how many rules will I have
for reinforce update rules here
two one for the MU one for the
sigma
right get me the reinforce update rules
and uh yeah so try to simplify it as
much as possible because when
you do the lawn mu I mean the
the lawn Pi derivatives you'll get
all kinds of we at constants coming
there so you can choose your Alpha appropriately
so that some of these constants get canceled out
so that I can have I can just like we did here
right I chose my row to be Theta and 1us Theta
likewise you can choose your constants in this
case also right the the alphas to be something
different so that you end up with a good uh
uh nice looking form okay great [Applause]